Guide to the Pavel Tchelitchew Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Pavel Tchelitchew collection
1907-1971
1928-1957
YCAL MSS 318
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
16.11
(33 boxes) + 1 roll
The collection includes correspondence, writings, photographs and printed material that document the life and work of Russian-born painter and set designer Pavel Tchelitchew. Correspondence includes letters between Tchelitchew and Edith Sitwell. Writings include the memoir of Tchelitchew's sister Alexandra Zaousailloff.
Tchelitchew, Pavel, 1898-1957
Zaoussailoff, Alexandra
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection contains material of mixed provenance acquired by purchase and donation from various sources.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Restricted Fragile in box 30 may be consulted only with permission of the appropriate curator. Preservation photocopies or photographic prints for reference use have been substituted in the main files.
Existence and Location of Copies
Correspondence with Edith Sitwell is available on microfilm.
Pavel Tchelitchew, 1898-1957
Russian-born painter, set designer, and costume designer, Pavel Tchelitchew emigrated in 1920. He lived in Berlin (1921-23) and Paris (1923-34) before moving to New York, where he lived with his partner Charles Henri Ford. He became a United States citizen in 1952 and died in Grottaferrata, Italy in 1957.
Tchelitchew's early painting was abstract in style, described as Constructivist and Futurist and influenced by his study with Aleksandra Ekster in Kiev. After emigrating to Paris he became associated with the Neoromanticism movement. He continuously experimented with new styles, eventually incorporating multiple perspectives and elements of surrealism and fantasy into his painting. As a set and costume designer, he collaborated with Serge Diaghliev and George Balanchine, among others.
In Paris Tchelitchew became acquainted with Gertrude Stein and, through her, the Sitwell and Gorer families. He and Edith Sitwell had a long-standing close friendship and they corresponded frequently.
Among Tchelitchew's well-known paintings are portraits of Natalia Glasko, Edith Sitwell and Gertrude Stein and the works Phenomena (1936-1938) and Cache Cache (1940-1942). He designed sets for Ode (Paris, 1928), L'Errante (Paris, 1933), Nobilissima Visione (London, 1938) and Ondine (Paris, 1939), among other productions.
Alexandra Zaoussailoff
Alexandra Zaoussailoff was sister of Pavel Tchelitchew; he addressed her as Choura (in Russian: Shura). She was the only other member of Tchelitchew's immediate family to emigrate from Russia and lived primarily in Paris.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of correspondence, writings, photographs, and printed material that document the artistic pursuits and personal life of Russian-born painter, set designer, and costume designer Pavel Tchelitchew. The material documents Tchelitchew's assessment of his own work, the conception and execution of many of his paintings and his business dealings with collectors, galleries and museums. In addition to documentation of Tchelitchew's life as an emigre, some material relates to his early life in Russia. A memoir of Tchelitchew's sister Alexandra Zaoussailoff (unpublished during her lifetime) recounts their childhood and describes their family background and upbringing. A few official documents attest to Tchelitchew's noble ancestry and his early education.
Most of the correspondence in the collection is with close friends and family, documenting both personal relationships and business activity. A portion of the correspondence relates specifically to Tchelitchew's business dealings with collectors, museums and galleries. Among the writings are short autobiographical sketches and self-reflective essays examining his development as an artist. The printed material includes collected images from magazines, postcards or books that he saved for their influence on his work. Photographs date chiefly from the years prior to the Second World War, when Tchelitchew, Zaoussailoff and friends spent their summers in Guermantes, France.
In addition to the primary research interest of Tchelitchew's life and work, the collection documents several aspects of twentieth century art and history. Tchelitchew's correspondence documents the cosmopolitan nature of artistic society before and after the Second World War in Europe and the United States. Family correspondence throughout the collection and Zaoussailoff's memoir document the social history of a post-Revolutionary aristocratic Russian family.
Arrangement
Organized into four series: I. Correspondence, 1923-1957. II Writings, 1934-1951. III. Printed Material, 1916-1971. IV Photographs and Other Papers, 1907-1970.
Appendix: Guide to the Microfilm
Series I, correspondence between Pavel Tchelitchew and Edith Sitwell and other papers found with Sitwell-Tchelitchew correspondence are available on microfilm.
Reel Boxes filmed Folders filmed Notes
1 9-10 165-182 Tchelitchew, to Edith Sitwell 1930-1945
2 10 183-199 Tchelitchew, to Edith Sitwell 1946-1957, undated
2 5-6 108-117 Sitwell, Edith, to Tchelitchew 1929-1932
3 6-7 118-133 Sitwell, Edith, to Tchelitchew 1932 -1941
4 7-8 134-144 Sitwell, Edith, to Tchelitchew 1942-1946
5 8-9 145-155 Sitwell, Edith, to Tchelitchew 1946-1949
6 9 156-158, 164 Sitwell, Edith, to Tchelitchew 1950-51, undated
6 1 7 Balston, T., to Tchelitchew 1931 Apr 28
6 1 16 Chatenay, Emile, to Tchelitchew 1934 Nov 6
6 2 44 Gorer, Geoffrey, to Tchelitchew 1930-32, n.d.
6 2 53 [James?], Edward, to Tchelitchew 1936 Jul 29
6 4 81 Koshkin, Vera, [to Tchelitchew?] 1935
6 4 82 Le Vincent, Charles, to Tchelitchew 1932 Jan 1
6 4 106 Saint Jean, Robert de, to Tchelitchew ca. 1931 Aug
6 11 204 Sitwell, Osbert, to Tchelitchew 1945 Feb 1
6 11 207 Speiser, Maurice, to Tchelitchew 1941 Feb 6
6 16 289 Zaroudnaia, Varvara, to Tchelitchew 1946
6 10 200 Edith Sitwell: "Notes on the nature of the greatest poetry", typescript carbon, corrected n.d.
6 10 201 Edith Sitwell: "A Sleepy Tune", holograph n.d.
6 10 202 Note by Tchelitchew accompanying gift of letters 1949 Feb 26
6 18 314 Sitwell, Edith, to Alexandra Zaoussailoff n.d.
Art, Modern -- 20th Century; Painters -- Russia (Federation) -- 20th Century -- Archives; Painters -- Soviet Union -- Archives; Painters -- United States -- Archives; Painting, American; Theater; Russia -- Emigration and immigration; Artists; Authors; Painters; Poets; Set designers; Women authors; LGBTQ resource; Ford, Charles Henri, 1908-2002; Gorer, Geoffrey, 1905-; Kochanski, Sofia; Sitwell, Edith, 1887-1964; Tanner, Allen; Tchelitchew, Pavel, 1898-1957; Tyler, Parker, 1904-1974; Zaoussailoff, Alexandra; Zarudnaia, Varvara Fedorovna; Ballets russes
- Correspondence, 1923-1957; Series I; 8.22; (18 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Pavel Tchelitchew Correspondence documents Tchelitchew's artistic and personal life and the business of selling, lending and exhibiting his paintings. It includes six boxes of letters to and from Edith Sitwell, documenting their close friendship and professional collaboration. Tchelitchew discusses his artistic projects, creative inspiration and the practicalities of showing and selling his paintings. Sitwell discusses her many writings and some letters include drafts of her poems.
  The correspondence also includes family letters, which provide a glimpse of the daily life of an aristrocratic family in the early Soviet era and include discussion of the family's difficult financal situation. Correspondence with his sister Alexandra documents their lives as emigres in Europe and the United States and their collaboration on matters related to Tchelitchew's career.
  Alexandra Zaousailloff Correspondence is with family members and friends and associates of Pavel Tchelitchew. Family correspondence relates news about the lives of sisters Varvara Zarudnaia and Mariia Klimenko in Russia; correspondence with others relates chiefly to matters related to Tchelitchew's career and to Zaousailloff's memoir.
  Arrangement
  Correspondence is organized under two headings: Pavel Tchelitchew Correspondence and Alexandra Zaoussailoff Correspondence. Arranged alphabetically under each heading.
  - Pavel Tchelitchew Correspondence
    Correspondence identified by first name only, unsorted general correspondence and unsorted business papers and correspondence are filed at the end of the alphabetical listing.
    Letters are incoming unless otherwise specified.
    - Arthur Tooth & Sons, Ltd., 1932-1938 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Askew, Kirk and Constance, incoming and outgoing, 1942-1957 (Box 1, Folder 2-4)
    - Austin, Charles, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Bachelard, Gaston, 1953-1957 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Includes drafts of an English translation of an essay by Bachelard on Tchelitchew.
    - Balston, Thomas, 1931 April 28 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Existence and Location of Copies
      Microfilm available.
    - Beaton, Cecil, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Berman, Leonid, 1952-1957 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Bobrow-Snieżyński, Andrzej, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Bonjean, Jacques, 1930-1952 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Bonney, Thérèse, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Buckle, Richard, 1954-1955 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Burns, Phil, outgoing
      - Incoming, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - Outgoing, 1952-1954 (Box 1, Folder 15)
        Includes transcripts made by Donald Gallup and a letter to Alice de la Mar.
    - Chatenay, Emile, 1934 November 6 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Chelishchev family, 1918-1939, undated (Box 1, Folder 17-25)
      Related Archival Materials note
      See also: Zarudnaia, Varvara
      Includes Pavel Tchelitchew's father Fedor, mother Nadezhda, and sisters Mariia (Klimenko) and Varvara (Zarudnaia).
      Includes letters addressed to Alexandra Zaoussailoff.
    - Columbia Records, 1952-1954 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Cowles Meyer, Fleur, 1952-1957 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Cremonini, Leonardo, 1952-1957 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Crevel, René, 1926-1930, undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - de la Mar, Alice, 1952-1957 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Diaghliev, Serge, 1928-1929 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Durlacher Bros., Inc.
      See: Askew, Kirk and Constance
    - Fini, Leonor, 1952-1957 (Box 2, Folder 32-33)
    - Fish, Doris and Morris, 1954-1957 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Flanner, Janet, undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Ford, Charles Henri, 1932-1956 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Fosburgh, James and Minnie, undated (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Galerie Pierre, 1926-1929 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Galerie Rive Gauche, 1956-1957 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Galleria d'Arte del Naviglio, 1954-1955 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Galleria Schneider, 1955-1956 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Garbat, A., outgoing, 1951-1952 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - George, Waldemar, 1928-1933 (Box 2, Folder 43)
      Includes a draft of "Humain trop humain ..." by George.
    - Gorer, Geoffrey, 1930-1955 (Box 2, Folder 44-47)
      Microfilm of letters from 1930-1932 available.
    - Green, Julien, 1931-1933, undated (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Hackett Galleries, 1930 (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - Hanover Gallery, 1949-1957 (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - Hill, Derek, undated (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - Hoyningen-Huene, George, 1952-1956 (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - James, Edward, 1932-1936 (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - Jennings, Oliver, 1952-1955 (Box 3, Folder 54)
    - Jouffroy, Alain, 1956-1957 (Box 3, Folder 55)
    - Jouvet, Louis, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 56)
    - Julien Levy Gallery, 1932-1951 (Box 3, Folder 57)
    - Kelleher, Patrick and Marion, 1956-1957 (Box 3, Folder 58)
    - Kirstein, Lincoln, 1939-1957 (Box 3, Folder 59)
      Includes a draft of an essay by Kirstein in Tchelitchew.
      Includes a draft of Medea: Or the Life of the Bees by Tchelitchew and George Balanchine.
    - Kochanski, Sofia (Zosia), outgoing, 1940-1957, undated (Box 3, Folder 60-78)
    - Kochno, Boris, outgoing, 1923-1953, undated (Box 3, Folder 79-80)
    - Koshkin, Vera, 1935 October 24 (Box 4, Folder 81)
    - Le Vincent, Charles, 1932 January 1 (Box 4, Folder 82)
    - Leibl, Marianna, 1953-1957 (Box 4, Folder 83)
    - Lifar, Serge, 1932-1933 (Box 4, Folder 84)
    - Louvre (Paris, France), 1931 November 5 (Box 4, Folder 85)
    - Loy, Mina, 1933, undated (Box 4, Folder 86)
    - Lynes, George Platt, 1954, undated (Box 4, Folder 87)
    - Lynes, Russell and Mildred, outgoing, 1955 December 8 (Box 4, Folder 88)
    - Magallanes, Nicholas, 1953, undated (Box 4, Folder 89)
    - Markevitch, Igor, 1931-1932, undated (Box 4, Folder 90)
    - Massine, Leonide, incoming and outgoing, undated (Box 4, Folder 91-92)
    - Masson, André, 1954, undated (Box 4, Folder 93)
    - Metropolitan Museum of Art, 1952 (Box 4, Folder 94)
    - Moore, Lamont, 1948-1956 (Box 4, Folder 95)
    - Museum of Modern Art (New York, N.Y.), 1953-1955 (Box 4, Folder 96)
      See also: Wheeler, Monroe
    - [Nabokov, Nicolas?], 1956, undated (Box 4, Folder 97)
    - Nikitina, Ekaterina Ivanovna, outgoing, 1951-1953 (Box 4, Folder 98)
    - Ottolenghi, Achille, 1954 (Box 4, Folder 99)
    - Palais des beaux-arts (Brussels, Belgium), 1955-1956 (Box 4, Folder 100)
    - Payne, Barbara, undated (Box 4, Folder 101)
    - Redfern Gallery, 1926, undated (Box 4, Folder 102)
    - Rindge, Agnes, 1933, undated (Box 4, Folder 103)
    - Rubinstein, Helena, 1934 (Box 4, Folder 104)
    - Sage, Kay, 1953-1957 (Box 4, Folder 105)
    - Saint Jean, Robert de, circa 1931 (Box 4, Folder 106)
    - Scott, Ruth Ford and Zachary, 1954-1957 (Box 4, Folder 107)
    - Sitwell, Edith
      - Incoming (Sitwell to Tchelitchew), 1929-1931 (Box 5, Folder 108-115)
      - Incoming (Sitwell to Tchelitchew), 1932-1935 (Box 6, Folder 116-124)
      - Incoming (Sitwell to Tchelitchew), 1936-1943 (Box 7, Folder 125-138)
      - Incoming (Sitwell to Tchelitchew), 1944-1948 (Box 8, Folder 139-152)
      - Incoming (Sitwell to Tchelitchew), 1949-1957, undated (Box 9, Folder 153-164)
        Letters from 1954-1957 and undated letters are not microfilmed.
      - Outgoing (Tchelitchew to Sitwell), 1930-1943 (Box 9, Folder 165-174)
      - Outgoing (Tchelitchew to Sitwell), 1944-1957, undated (Box 10, Folder 175-199)
      - Other Papers found with Sitwell-Tchelitchew correspondence, 1949, undated (Box 10, Folder 200-203)
        Includes drafts of "Notes on the nature of the greatest poetry" and "A sleepy tune" by Edith Sitwell, and a note from Tchelitchew about restricting access to the correspondence until 2000.
    - Sitwell, Osbert, 1931, 1945 (Box 11, Folder 204)
      Microfilm available of letter from 1945.
    - Soby, James Thrall, 1954-1957 (Box 11, Folder 205)
    - Société Générale, 1934-1949 (Box 11, Folder 206)
    - Speiser, Maurice, 1941 February 6 (Box 11, Folder 207)
    - Spies, Walter, undated (Box 11, Folder 208)
    - Stephan Lion, Inc., 1957 (Box 11, Folder 209)
    - Sturdza, Dimitri, 1933 (Box 11, Folder 210)
    - Tate, Allen, 1955 October 4 (Box 11, Folder 211)
    - Tchelitchew family
      See: Chelishchev family
    - Tennant, Stephen, 1934-1954 (Box 11, Folder 212)
    - Tyler, Parker, 1952-1957 (Box 11, Folder 213)
    - Verdue, Germaine, 1956-1957 (Box 11, Folder 214)
    - Vogel, Lucien, 1950 (Box 11, Folder 215)
    - Volodine, George, 1957 November 11 (Box 11, Folder 216)
    - Watson, Peter, 1933-1934, undated (Box 11, Folder 217)
    - Watt, Sandy, 1934, undated (Box 11, Folder 218)
    - Wescott, Glenway, 1955, undated (Box 11, Folder 219)
      Includes a draft of an essay by Wescott on Tchelitchew.
    - Wheeler, Monroe, 1932-1956 (Box 11, Folder 220)
    - Whitney, Betsey, 1957 (Box 11, Folder 221)
    - Wild, Renato, 1953-1956, undated (Box 11, Folder 222)
    - Yale University Library, 1952-1953 (Box 11, Folder 223)
      Includes transcripts of letters from Tchelitchew to Gertrude Stein.
    - Young, Stark, 1953-1955 (Box 11, Folder 224)
    - Zaoussailoff, Alexandra
      - Incoming, 1928-1957 (Box 12, Folder 225-227)
      - Outgoing, 1922-1930 (Box 12, Folder 228-237)
      - Outgoing, 1931-1937 (Box 13, Folder 238-250)
      - Outgoing, 1938-1946 (Box 14, Folder 251-269)
      - Outgoing, 1947-1957, undated (Box 15, Folder 270-287)
      - Outgoing telegrams, 1934-1957 (Box 15, Folder 288)
    - Zarudnaia, Varvara, incoming and outgoing, 1945-1948 (Box 16, Folder 289-290)
    - _____, Aleksandr, 1930s (Box 16, Folder 291)
    - _____, Andre, 1956, undated (Box 16, Folder 292)
    - _____, "Baby", 1953-54, undated (Box 16, Folder 293)
    - _____, Ekaterina, 1952, undated (Box 16, Folder 294)
    - _____, Elsie, 1952, undated (Box 16, Folder 295)
    - _____, "Kot", 1954-1957 (Box 16, Folder 296)
    - _____, Petr, 1921-1922 (Box 16, Folder 297)
    - General correspondence, circa 1921-1956 (Box 16, Folder 298-301)
      Letters are unsorted within the folders.
    - Business correspondence and papers (Box 17, Folder 302-304)
      Business correspondence and papers document Tchelitchew's exhibitions and the sale of his works. The papers include notes and lists of paintings detailing dimensions and titles. Also included are immigration documents, medical records and financial records. Official documents are also filed in Series IV.
      Letters and papers are unsorted within the folders.
  - Alexandra Zaousailloff Correspondence
    Incoming unless otherwise indicated.
    - Böhm, Hans, 1931 March 3 (Box 18, Folder 305)
    - Ford, Charles Henri, 1952-1957 (Box 18, Folder 306)
    - Galerie Pierre, undated (Box 18, Folder 307)
    - Klimenko, Mariia, 1964, undated (Box 18, Folder 308)
    - Lopez-Willshaw, Patricia, undated (Box 18, Folder 309)
    - Moore, Lamont and Henrietta, outgoing, 1945-1970 (Box 18, Folder 310-313)
      Includes excerpts translated into English by Lamont Moore.
    - Sitwell, Edith, 1930-1946, undated (Box 18, Folder 314-315)
      Microfilm available of one undated letter.
    - Zarudnaia, Varvara, 1934-1935 (Box 18, Folder 316)
    - Unidentified, 1931, undated (Box 18, Folder 317)
- Writings, 1934-1951; Series II; 0.83; (2 boxes)
  Arranged roughly by topic.
  Includes notes on his art by Pavel Tchelitchew, a lecture by Tchelitchew, Alexandra Zaousailloff's memoir, and writings of others about Tchelitchew. Also includes a script of Ondine by Jean Giraudoux, for which Tchelitchew designed the set in 1939. Tchelitchew's notes on his art were likely written to aid in the preparation of exhibit catalogs or other material on Tchelitchew. Zaousailloff's memoir recounts the life of the Chelishchev family in Russia until the time of Pavel Tchelitchew's emigration (circa 1898-1920). Included here are drafts of French and English translations of the memoir; the Russian-language original is not part of the collection.
  All writings are typescript drafts unless otherwise indicated.
  - Notes on his art, by Pavel Tchelitchew
    - Autobiographical notes on Tchelitchew's development as an artist, holograph, undated (Box 19, Folder 318-319)
      Includes a transcription by Lamont Moore.
    - Autobiographical notes on Tchelitchew's development as an artist, undated (Box 19, Folder 320-321)
      Includes English translation by Lamont Moore.
    - Notes on "Cache-Cache", undated (Box 19, Folder 322)
    - Notes on perspective, holograph, undated (Box 19, Folder 323)
    - Notes on Tchelitchew's life and art, holograph and typescript, undated (Box 19, Folder 324)
  - Martin A. Ryerson Lecture, "In connection with the Gertrude Stein exhibition," by Pavel Tchelitchew, 1951 February 20 (Box 19, Folder 325)
    Accession label: "Gift of the Gallery of Fine Arts (Lamont Moore) 1951."
  - Memoir, by Alexandra Zaoussailoff
    Zaoussailoff's memoir exists in several versions. It was presumably written in Russian, though the Russian-language version is not in the collection. Parker Tyler and Allen Tanner used a French translation as a source for their English translations. The collection contains no record of a printed verison of the memoir.
    - French-language version and English translation by Lamont Moore, typescript, undated (Box 19, Folder 326-329)
      Microfilm available of the second draft of English translation by Lamont Moore.
      The French-language version was translated from the original Russian by an unidentified Parisian friend of Zaoussailoff.
    - French-language version, typescript, and English translation by Allen Tanner, holograph, undated (Box 20, Folder 330-333)
      Includes notes by Parker Tyler, who used Tanner's translation as a source for his book The Divine Comedy of Pavel Tchelitchew. This material was damaged by a fire in Tyler's apartment.
  - Notes on Tchelitchew, by Allen Tanner, undated (Box 20, Folder 334-336)
    Used by Parker Tyler as a source for his book The divine comedy of Pavel Tchelitchew. This material was damaged by a fire in Parker Tyler's apartment.
  - "Data on Paul Tchelitchew whose show opens December 12th, 1934," [by Allen Tanner?] (Box 20, Folder 337)
  - "Speech at opening of Pavel Tchelitchew exhibition," by Edith Sitwell, undated (Box 20, Folder 338)
  - Foreword to an unidentified exhibition catalog, by Osbert Sitwell, undated (Box 20, Folder 339)
  - Notes on Tchelitchew, by Konstanty Jelenski, undated (Box 20, Folder 340)
  - Ondine, by Jean Giraudoux, 1939 (Box 20, Folder 341-343)
  - "Parallel lines will meet .... Einstein, Theory of Relativity," by Alice D. Fenton, 1950s (Box 20, Folder 344)
- Printed Material, 1916-1971; Series III; 2.5; (6 boxes)
  Arranged roughly by type of material.
  Printed material includes catalogs and announcements related to the exhibition and sale of Tchelitchew's paintings, material that Tchelitchew collected as inspiration ("Influences"), newspaper clippings about Tchelitchew and serial publications about art and theater from the early twentieth century, some of which contain material about Tchelitchew. Also includes programs for theater and ballet performances, for many of which Tchelitchew designed costumes or sets.
  - Catalogs and announcements for exhibits of Tchelitchew's art, 1928-1971 (Box 21, Folder 345-359)
  - Guest register for an exhibit of Tchelitchew's art, 1956
  - Programs for theater and ballet performances, 1916-1929 (Box 21, Folder 360-367)
    Includes programs for Ballets Russes performances (1921-1929). One 1929 catalog has a graphite drawing in graphite of a man's head on the back. Attributed to Giorgio De Chirico.
  - Programs for theater and ballet performances, 1930-1939, undated (Box 22, Folder 368-375)
  - Broadside for Ondine, 1939
  - "Influences", 1937-1956, undated (Box 22, Folder 376-387)
    Postcards, photographs and magazine images collected by Tchelitchew that influenced his art.
  - "Influences", 1937-1956, undated (Box 23, Folder 388-404)
  - Clippings, 1920s (Box 23, Folder 405-406)
  - Clippings, 1933-1964 (Box 24, Folder 407-422)
  - Serial publications on art and theater, 1921-1962, undated (Box 25, Folder 423-436)
  - Monographs on art and theater, some inscribed to Tchelitchew, 1922-1956 (Box 26, Folder 437-445)
    Includes Cirque by Ossip Lubitch, 10 etchings and aquatints after a poem by George Roualt, inscribed to Tchelitchew and signed by the artist.
- Photographs and Other Papers, 1907-1970; Series IV; 0.83; (2 boxes)
  Other Papers are organized into two subseries: Photographs and Other Material. Other material is arranged roughly by type of material.
  Includes photographs, official documents, diaries, engagement books, two sketches by Tchelitchew and one audio recording of a speech by Tchelitchew.
  - Photographs
    Photographs are snapshots taken in Guermantes, France and include acquaintances who visited Tchelitchew there.
    Photographs also include portraits, most stored in Oversize, of Tchelitchew, Edith Sitwell, Charles Henri Ford and others, photographed by Cecil Beaton and George Platt Lynes.
    - Abdy, L., undated